Among the freshly blooming dandelions
And the droplets of water which couldn't quite become snow
I thought I could make out a face stained with tears
So I offered my umbrella without a second thought
Is going left or right correct?
The path ended before I could really decide
But surely the right call is the one which spares that special someone
From any painful experiences
So with a little courage, take that plunge forward
If everything's all crooked, take an oblique path
As long as you're moving forward, you'll find the light
Like those little birds that huddle together and cry out in unison
We'll definitely ring in the start of a new season
And so spring will embrace us once more
We'll splash paint on some new pages
We became fast friends, we enjoyed some good food
We might've even argued a little
But we carry those little moments in our hearts
As reasons which compel us toward a future that can't possibly be mistaken
No matter how many times we find ourselves lost among sunlit trees
Today has been carried here by the winds on a one-way ticket
That blooms into a perfect day
Passing Time
Let's see.
（医師）
え〜っと…　上が135で 下が80
135 over 80.
ふ〜む…
Not bad, Some.
（医師）
いいんじゃねえの？　相米(そめ)ちゃん
ふむ…
All right.
（相米二(そめじ)）よ〜し…
That's what I'm talking about.
（相米二）さすが俺だ
Your blood pressure has gone down quite a bit.
血圧は だいぶ下がった
でも 薬は出しとく　続けてくれよ
But I'm going to give you more medicine.
Keep taking it.
Sure thing.
おう！
Lay it on me!
バ〜ンと出してくんな
About three months' worth.
３か月分くらい
Sakuma, M.D.
（医師）バカ　そんなに出せるか
３週間分だよ
Idiot. I can't give you that much.
You'll get three weeks' worth.
Come back again next month for more.
また来月 取りに来な
All right, fine.
（相米二）チッ！　しかたねえな
ヘヘッ…　また来るか
Guess I'll see you then.
You really have changed though, Some.
しっかし
相米ちゃんも変わったもんだよ
昔は“医者なんざアテにはしねえ”
A long time ago, you were like,
"I'm not counting on any doctor!"
You used to say, "I'll live how I want to and die whenever!"
“俺は 好きに生きて
好きに死ぬ”って言ってたのにな
Well, my wife and daughter left me with three little ones.
（相米二）ばあさんと娘が—
ひなっ子を３匹も残して
逝っちまったからな
For them, I'm all they have.
あいつらには
もう俺しかいねえんだ
Come hell or high water, I have to stay alive until all three of them are married off.
３人とも
きっちり嫁に出すまでは—
俺は 石にかじりついてでも
生きなきゃなんねえ
あいつらのことを独りぼっちで—
No way can I let them stand in front
of that gold leaf folding screen alone.
金屏風の前へ立たせるわけにゃ
断じていかねえんだよ
相米ちゃん…
Some...
（相米二）だが しかし…
But still...
（モモ）ハァ〜ッ…
With Momo, it'd help me out if she got married as soon as possible.
モモだけはな…
“なるたけ早めに
嫁いでくれると助かるな”って…
Hmm...
The youngest, huh?
末っ子か…　いくつだっけ？
How old is she again?
Sq
Squ
Sque
Squee
Squeee
Mud balls
Preschooler
She's still in preschool.
まだ保育園だからなぁ
If she got married just after twenty, I'd be...
二十歳ちょいで
行ってくれたとしても 俺は…
in my mid-90s?!
90半ばか…
（医師）ごめん 相米ちゃん
俺も そこまで診てやれんわ…
I'm sorry.
I can't look after you for that long.
（ひなた）試験まで あと５日…
Five more days until the entrance exam.
（ひなた）
ハァ〜ッ！　ドキドキするよ！
I'm so nervous!
Groan
Argh
Meowww
Aowww
The anxiety is spreading
Meowww
Aowww
Got lured in
and crying too
Meowww
Aowww
（零(れい)）
できることは みんなやったよ
Meowww
Aowww
You've done everything you could.
Meowww
Aowww
苦手だった証明問題も
平均80点以上になったし
Meowww
Aowww
You even got your weakest area, proofs, up to an average score in the 80s.
Meowww
Aowww
だから 大丈夫
So you'll be fine.
あとは まんべんなく
おさらいって感じでいこう
Now we should just review everything thoroughly.
And if there's anything you're still unsure of, we'll practice it again with a worksheet.
…で 気になる所があったら そこを
もう一度 問題集で解いてみよう
（零）あっ そうだ
Oh, that's right.
高橋(たかはし)君
Takahashi said he's going to a private school in Kouchi in Shikoku thanks to a recommendation, huh?
推薦で 四国の高知義塾(こうちぎじゅく)に行くの
決まったんだってね
Huh?
Hina, did you not...
ひなちゃん もしかして…
四国の？
In Shikoku?
（零）その彼女の—
When I saw her surprised face,
which looked like that of a young child,
小さな子供みたいに
驚いた顔を見て—
僕は 小さな卵を—
it felt like I had...
クシャッと
割ってしまったような
broken a small egg.
気持ちになった
（ひなた）
私 明帝(めいてい)大付属に行くって聞いて…
I'd heard he was going to the high school affiliated with Meitei University.
（ひなた）
前に そう言ってたから…
That's what he said before.
So...
だから…
Shikoku?
四国…
That's so far away.
そんな遠い所に…
（零）もう知ってると思ってた
言わなければよかった
I thought she already knew about it.
I wish I'd never said anything.
俺 何やってんだ…
こんな試験ギリギリになって
What the hell am I doing?
Her exam is just days away.
せっかく 彼女 頑張ってきたのに…
And she worked so hard for this too.
あんな顔させるなんて…
I made her feel so terrible.
そして あんな顔させるのは…
But she only feels this way...
やっぱり高橋君なんだなって…
because it's Takahashi.
Oh, Hina, are you out grocery shopping?
（女性）おや ひなちゃん
お買い物？　偉いねえ
That's wonderful.
（ひなた）
山田(やまだ)のおばあちゃん こんにちは
Hello, Mrs. Yamada.
（ひなた）
子供のころから変わらない私の町
My town hasn't changed
since I was a kid.
近所の風景
Nor has the scenery of the neighborhood.
Drink milk to be healthy
Takahashi Milk
そして 商店街の外れには…
And at the edge of the shopping district...
Hokkaido
Milk Pudding
カレーの匂い
I smell curry.
そっか
高橋君の家(うち)は 今晩はカレーか
I see.
Takahashi's family is having curry for dinner tonight.
I bet he'll be happy about that.
喜ぶだろうな
高橋君 カレー大好きだもんな
Takahashi does love curry.
（高橋）
川本(かわもと)ん家(ち)のカレーって すごいな！
Your guys' curry is awesome!
四国か…
Shikoku, huh?
遠いな
That's far from here.
ちほちゃんの岩手も 遠いな
And Chiho in Iwate is far from here.
お母さんも おばあちゃんも…
Mom, Grandma,
お父さんも…
and Dad too.
いつも そうだ
It's always like that.
当たり前のあしたが
当たり前にやって来て—
I take it for granted that tomorrow will come like it always does,
ずっと いつまでも
普通に会えるんだって思っちゃって
and that I'll always be able to see everyone.
そして びっくりするんだ
But then I get a surprise.
いつも いつも こんなふうに…
Just like this,
time after time...
（あかり）
桐山(きりやま)君　ホントにいいの？
Kiriyama, are you sure you don't mind?
It's fine.
大丈夫です
I'll stay here until you get back, Akari.
あかりさんが戻ってくるまで
僕 いますから
Besides, you helped me so much last year.
それに 去年は
僕が お世話になったんですから
（モモ）ンンッ！
（あかり）ごめんね
I'm sorry.
There's suddenly a party at my aunt's bar.
おばさまのお店も
パーティーが入って…
モモ おじいちゃん家 お泊まりなの
I'm gonna stay over at Grandpa's place!
なるべく早く戻るから
I'll come back as soon as I can.
はい
Okay.
（ひなた）どうしよう…
What should I do?
The entrance exam is the day
after tomorrow and I'm like this.
あさって 入試なのに こんな…
大丈夫　勉強は もう十分やったよ
You'll be fine.
You studied plenty.
あとは ゆっくり休んで
体調を少しでも戻そう
Now you just need to rest up and recuperate as much as possible.
熱下がらなかったら どうしよう…
What'll I do if the fever doesn't go down?
覚えたこと…
What if...
I forget everything I've learned?
みんな忘れちゃったら…
忘れないよ
You won't forget.
大丈夫
It'll be okay.
もうちょっとしたら
おかゆ食べて 薬のもう
In a little while, you can have some porridge, and then take some medicine.
Until then, get some sleep.
それまで寝てな
Okay.
Well, it's easier to sleep if it's dark, so I'll close the door.
（零）じゃ
暗くしたほうが眠れるから閉めるよ
Okay.
何かしてほしいことがあったら
呼んで
Call for me if you need anything.
I'll be right next door.
僕は隣にいるから
Okay.
（零）そして 受験の朝
By the morning of the exam,
her fever had dropped considerably, to just over 37 degrees.
熱は かなり下がって
37度ちょっとになった
（あかり）
ひな　桐山君 迎えに来てくれたよ
Hina!
Kiriyama has come to pick you up!
What? Rei's here?
（ひなた）えっ？　零ちゃん？
You didn't have to go to the trouble. I'll be okay!
わざわざ いいよ　大丈夫だよ
いや でも僕 ちょうど休みだし
Well, it's my day off anyway.
From school?
（ひなた）学校は？
Well, you and everyone else taking the exam will be there, so we don't have class today.
だって ひなちゃんたち
受けに来るから 僕らは授業ないよ
Oh, that's right.
（ひなた）あっ そっか
Hina, good luck!
ひな　頑張って
See you later!
いってらっしゃい
Be careful of the snow. Don't fail—
雪 気をつけて
すべらな…　ハッ！
Eek
I-I mean, don't trip.
（あかり）こ… 転ばないようにね
（モモ）ウオーッ！
（ひなた）うん いってきます
Right! See you later!
（ひなた）
熱がある間 私は ずっと—
During the time I had the fever,
I kept thinking about all the people I'd lost,
いなくなってしまった人たちの
ことばかり考えて—
涙がこぼれて止まらなかった
and my tears wouldn't stop flowing.
（零）カバン持つよ
I'll hold your bag.
（ひなた）えっ？　いいよ　大丈夫
（零）道 凍ってて危ないから
That's okay. I've got it.
The sidewalk's all icy, so it could be dangerous.
ほら
Here.
（ひなた）ありがとう
Thanks.
Kiriyama,
なんか桐山君って お母さんみたい
you're kind of like a mother.
What?
ああ…　それ なんか
前にも誰かに言われた気がする
I feel like someone told me that before.
（ひなた）でも…
But...
ああ…　でも そうだ
But that's right.
零ちゃんは 突然 私の前に現れた
Rei suddenly appeared before me.
Mom, Grandma,
お母さん おばあちゃん
ひなを どうか見守っていて
please watch over Hina.
Crescent Moon
（相米二）頑張れ ひな
Good luck, Hina.
ウワッ… ワアッ！
アアッ…　ひなちゃん　大丈夫？
Hina! Are you all right?!
すべっ…
You f—
No, um, I mean...
…ったんじゃなくて え〜っと
大丈夫！　こ… 転んだだけ
I'm fine!
I-I just tripped!
（ひなた）そうだ
That's right.
遠くへ
行ってしまうものばかりじゃない
Not everyone has gone far away.
消えていくものばかりじゃない
Not everyone has disappeared.
それを絶対に忘れてはいけないんだ
I mustn't ever forget that.
Passing Time
Spring Comes
（ひなた）ハ… ハワワッ…
Quiver
ワッ… ウワ〜ッ！
Wow!
Quiver
Piping hot
Sizzle
Heap of juicy
deep-fried chicken
E
g
p
l
a
n
t
a
n
d
m
e
a
t
g
r
a
t
i
n
w
i
t
h
p
l
e
n
t
y
o
f
c
h
e
s
T
u
n
a
d
s
o
f
t
b
o
i
l
e
d
g
m
a
c
r
o
n
i
s
a
l
d
G
a
r
l
i
c
t
o
a
s
t
M
i
n
r
i
c
e
b
a
l
s
a
n
d
s
w
e
t
p
i
c
k
l
e
d
a
i
k
o
n
r
a
d
i
s
h
（一同）ひな！　合格おめでとう！
Hina, congratulations on passing!
Congrats
I-It's like a mountain of fried meat!
か… 唐揚げが山のよう！
Huge pile
あちち…　ジュワッと来た
It's juicy!
Huff
Grabbing it with her hands
And the eggplant gratin!
そして ナスのグラタン
うれしい！　チーズが こんなに…
I'm so happy!
Look at all this cheese!
山盛りのマカロニサラダ
ツナと半熟たまごも たっぷり！
A huge pile of macaroni salad!
With lots of tuna and soft boiled eggs!
Huff
What do you think?
どう？　ひなの大好物で
まとめてみました
Huff
I made all your favorites, Hina.
Hohoho
It's really delicious!
すんごく おいしいです！
（あかり）
さあ た〜んと お上がりなさい
All right, everyone! Fill up!
今日は 唐揚げは飲み物だから
For tonight, fried foods are the beverages.
Since we're celebrating, I got carried away and deep-fried two kilograms of chicken.
お姉ちゃん お祝いだから—
張り切って
鶏肉２キロ揚げちゃったから
（美咲(みさき)）
に… ２キロ？　飲み物って…
T-Two kilos?! As beverages?
Akari
Akari, wait... Stop...
Wait
Stop
Hina, congratulations!
（モモ）ひなちゃん おめでとう
（ひなた）ありがとう モモ
Thank you, Momo!
I'm gonna go to kindergarten soon too.
モモも
年長さんになるんだよ
（あかり）ホンット…
Really, now...
My little Hina is becoming a high school student.
あの小さかった ひなが
もう高校生だなんて
早いわね　私が年を取るわけだわ
Time sure flies.
I'm getting old.
No, Akari! Knock it off!
こら！　あかり　ダメよ！
オカン禁止！
No mom-talk!
You're still only 23!
あんた まだ23歳だから！
でも
ホントに 零ちゃんのおかげだよ
But it's really all thanks to Rei.
Because he helped me with math,
I was able to solve a lot of mysteries!
零ちゃんが数学見てくれたから—
謎が いっぱい解けたもの
Like proofs!
証明問題とかの…
True, your math average has gone up
30 points since Rei started tutoring you.
（あかり）数学の平均点—
零ちゃんに見てもらってから
30点近く上がったもんね
Even though you really didn't like math!
あんなに数学 苦手だったのに
Whoa, that's impressive, kid!
（相米二）なんだ　すげえな 坊主
やっぱ棋士ってのは頭がいいんだな
I guess professional shogi players are smart cookies.
ホンットに ありがとうね
私も“零君”って呼んでいい？
Thank you so much.
Can I call you Rei too?
Eat some more.
もっと食べて！
Keep eating!
どんどん食べて！
Uh, th-thank you.
Heap
えっ？　ああ…
ありがとうございます
The night
before
the exam
(Flashback)
The night
before
the exam
(Flashback)
What?!
Rattle
ふ… ２人っきりで
家に置いてきたですって!?
What?!
Rattle
Y-You left the two of them alone in the house?!
What?!
Rattle
Kiriyama is that boy who's always over, right?
桐山君って
あの いつもの子でしょう？
How old is he now?
今いくつ？
ええっ！　高２？
A second-year?
You left a third-year junior high schooler and a
second-year high schooler home alone this late?
あんた 中３と高２の男女を—
こんな夜更けに
２人っきりにしてきたの？
Wh-What'll you do if something happens?
なななな…
何かあったら どうすんの？
If they make a mistake, it'll be too late!
間違いがあってからじゃ遅いのよ
You need to go home right now!
あんた 今すぐ帰んなさい
Wh-What'll we do if something happens to Hina?
ひ… ひなに何かあったら
どうすんの？
Calm down.
It's all right, Aunty.
大丈夫よ おばさま
心配すること何もないわ
There's nothing to worry about.
It's all right?!
“大丈夫”って
あんた 何をそんな悠長な…
How can you be so blasé?
（あかり）だって…
Well,
桐山君ですもの
we're talking about Kiriyama here.
ウフッ…
And then,
the next day
(Flashback 2)
And then,
the next day
(Flashback 2)
（美咲）ねえ ちょっと お父さん
大丈夫なの？
Hey, Dad, are you okay with this?
いくら いい子で
勉強を教えてくれるからって—
Even if he's well-behaved and helping her study,
I can't believe you're letting a young animal have the run of an all-female house.
女だけの家に
ヤングなアニマルを—
こうも しょっちゅう
出入りさせるなんて…
What are you going on about?
（相米二）
なんでえ なんでえ いきなりよぅ
What'll we do if something happens to Hina?
ひなに何かあったら
どうするのよ？
大丈夫
It's fine.
だって 坊主だぜ
After all, we're talking about the kid!
No way! Nothing's gonna happen!
ないない
何にも起こりゃしねえって
Not only Akari, but Dad too!
あかりのみならず
お父さんまでにも！
They fully trust a second-year high school boy?
ここまで信用されきっている
高２男子って 一体…
Is he really that sheepish?
それ 何て安全パイ？
I worry about the future.
未来が思いやられるっていうか—
年ごろの男子として
いかがなものかと…
I mean, I have doubts about boys these days.
Go on, eat.
さあ 食べて　これも これも…
This and this!
ホントに ありがとうね
Really, thank you so much!
Sympathy
ありがとうございます…　うん？
Thank you.
（シロちゃん）ニャ〜ッ…
Pet me, pet me, pet me right now!
なでて なでて　今すぐ なでて
ニャ〜ッ…
零ちゃん　４月から よろしくね
Rei, I'm looking forward to April.
僕のほうこそ
Me too.
僕も 野口(のぐち)先輩とか
将科(しょうか)部のみんなが卒業しちゃうから
Noguchi and the other members
of the Sho-sci Club are graduating,
ひなちゃんが入ってきてくれて
うれしいよ
so I'm happy that you're coming to my school.
あと なんだか
先生も ものすごく喜んでたよ
And for some reason, Mr. Hayashida is thrilled about it too.
（ひなた）ホント？
Really?
That's the teacher I met when
we did the flume noodles, right?
流しそうめんのときの先生だよね？
うれしい！
That makes me so happy!
Yes!
（林田(はやしだ)）イエス！　よし 来た！
イ〜エス！
Here it comes!
Yes!
アア…　先生？
Mr. Hayashida?
零ちゃんには ホントに
何てお礼を言ったらいいか…
I really don't know how to thank you.
Even though you had a lot of your own work to do,
零ちゃん
お仕事も いっぱいあるのに—
you came here several times a week.
週に何度も来てもらって…
大丈夫だよ
ここにいても勉強してたから
Don't worry.
I was studying here too.
（零）それには ひどく気をつけた
Besides, I was incredibly careful.
If I got poor results,
僕がヘタな成績を残したら
彼女が 自分のせいと思うから—
she would've thought it was her fault,
so I played each and every match as carefully as possible.
１局１局が 隅々まで丁寧に指せた
それは
今までとは違う向き合い方だった
It was a different way of facing
things than I've done up to now.
Kid, you have two more class-promotion matches left this season, right?
坊主は 今期の順位戦は
あと２局くらいか？
あ〜 はい
Oh, yes.
今 ８勝です
Right now I'm at eight wins.
E-Eight wins in a row?!
は… ８連勝？
昇級ってことか？　Ｂ２へ？
So you'll get promoted to B2?!
Yes, unless something really bad happens.
はい
ものすごい何かが起きなければ
You say it so matter-of-factly.
そんなサラッと…
Hina, he's fine! In that world,
the kid is as terrifying as an ogre!
ひな　大丈夫だぞ
坊主は あっちの世界では
お… 鬼みてえに怖(こえ)えから
Oh man, this guy is scary!
ヤダ この人　こわっ…
鬼？　零ちゃんが？
Ogre? Rei?
Promoted?
昇級？
きっと すごいことなんだね
That's a great thing, right?
Um, uh,
え〜っと え〜っと…
（ひなた）良かった！
（モモ）プハ〜ッ！
thank goodness!
Hina, more soda, please.
ひなちゃん
ジュース もっとください
Soda?
ジュース？　何にする？
What kind?
Cola!
I hate to see her cry or be troubled about something.
（零）僕は 彼女が泣いたり
困ったりするのが好きじゃない
You're too young for that.
Then orange soda!
Okay, hold on.
I can't stand the idea of her being in trouble with me not knowing about it.
僕の知らない場所で
ピンチに立たされたりとか—
耐えられない
だから 僕の手の届く所に
来てくれると聞いて—
So when I heard she wanted to come to a place that was within my reach,
絶対に受からせようと思った
I wanted to make sure she was accepted.
それまで 僕は
自分が正しいか間違ってるかは—
Until then, I thought that whether what I did was right or wrong
裁判みたいに—
was something that other people would decide, as if in a trial.
他人に決めてもらわないと
いけないことだと思っていた
だけど あの日…
But then on that day,
when she said, "What I did was definitely not wrong,"
（零）“私のしたことは
間違ってない”と—
不安でいっぱいの中でも—
even though she was full of anxiety,
決して 自分の心の舵(かじ)を
しっかり握って離さない彼女に…
she still kept a firm grip on the helm of her heart.
僕は…
I found...
自分の中にはなかった光を見つけた
a light within myself that I didn't have before.
（零）そうだ
That's right.
僕の一部分は 間違いなく…
Without a doubt,
on that day,
あの日…
彼女に…
she made...
作ってもらったんだ
a part of me.
Rei.
（幸田(こうだ)）零
（零）お父さん…
Dad.
（幸田）今日 勝って
なんとかギリギリ 降級点は免れた
I won today, so I barely managed to avoid a demotion.
来期もＢ２でやれそうだ
Looks like I'll be in B2 next season.
（幸田）前回の続きができるかもな
Maybe we can pick up where we left off last time,
零…
Rei.
（零）はい
Yes,
お父さん
Dad.
Spring Comes
Surrounded by a landscape on the verge of permanent stasis
I found myself searching for something
I took up a mask to make my pitifully weak self appear stable
And donned it boldly
The sound of my frozen footsteps as I walked along the river
Was easily overpowered by the roar of a passing train
Yet I kept chanting "I just gotta take another step" to myself
Over and over again
Can you hear me proclaiming that I'm standing right here?
Even in bare feet I can go wherever the hell I want
I don't know where I might find myself at the end
I can't begin to guess, but I can just ink in
A new landscape to suit me as I go
Next Episode Preview
Episode 44
（零）２人とも
卒業おめでとう
Both of you,
congratulations on graduating.
Wait a second.
（高橋）
ちょっと待ってください
When are you leaving?
（零）いつ行くの？
Shall we get started?
（ひなた）
そろそろ行きますか！
Hina! Here!
（モモ）
ひなちゃん　これ！
I'm going to do my best here too.
（ひなた）
私も ここで頑張るね
My little sister is too cute!
（あかり）
かわいすぎる
私の妹が！
It was a failure.
（ひなた）失敗した
もう外には出ない…
I'm never leaving the house again.
Illustration: Koyama Chuuya
（ひなた）いよいよ
春から高校生かぁ
It's almost spring,
so I'll be a high school student, huh?
零君と同じ学校
楽しみだな
I'm looking forward to going
to the same school as Rei.